<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Samruddhi Dodal | Homepage</title>
    <description>Learn something new. Everyday. //this is an attempt to learn to code</description>
    <link>http://localhost:4000/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>2020-09-23</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 23 Sep 2020 12:23:16 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.8.7</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>IIT Bombay Placement Diaries</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;profile-at-a-glance&quot;&gt;Profile at a Glance:&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dual Degree student, MEMS dept with a Minor in Management.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;internships-&quot;&gt;Internships :&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Junior Field Engineer at Schlumberger
Supply chain internship (plant-based) at Mondelez India Foods (Cadbury)
Business Analyst – Dhanvikas financial services (early stage, part of founding team)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;positions-of-responsibility&quot;&gt;Positions of responsibility:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Events Manager, E-Cell (3rd year)
Design Convener, Institute Cultural Council (2nd year)
ISMP &amp;amp; DAMP Mentor (5th year)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;others&quot;&gt;Others:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Semester exchange to Politecnico di Milano (Sem 4.1)
Project on Blockchain &amp;amp; its Applications – Deutsche Bank | Manch&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;choice-of-profile&quot;&gt;Choice of profile:&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Deciding the kind of companies and profiles you should sit for is the first &amp;amp; foremost step of the placement season – and it should begin (ideally) much before the sem begins. This will also help you build your resume in a way that works best for a particular profile. You should choose a profile on the basis of &lt;b&gt;your interests&lt;/b&gt;, and your &lt;b&gt;past experience&lt;/b&gt; in these, if any.
Understand which companies come for placements in these sectors and get a detailed idea of the nature of work, future prospects, and resolve any other doubts you may have by &lt;b&gt;talking to seniors.&lt;/b&gt;
It is best to selectively prepare for 1 or 2 types of profiles/sectors really well rather than preparing for everything (trust me, there isn’t enough time for that). Also, it is important to have backup options in case there are few companies for the sector you have chosen. I would like to highlight here that the best way to go about this is to talk to as many seniors and really get to understand what the work entails, since that will help you have a clear perspective during the entire process. Post this, focus only on sector-specific prep for resume, tests, and interview process.
Using my experience from internships – analyzing which parts I liked more, talking to mentors, friends and seniors, and seeing that it was in line with my future aspirations, I decided to go for management consulting. I did not have a concrete backup option – I thought I could go for FMCG, or non-core (business analyst, etc) roles – however I sometimes felt stressed due to this as December approached, and hence would strongly recommend everyone to have backups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;resume-building&quot;&gt;Resume Building:&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PT Cell allows you to upload multiple resumes (5 in total, if I remember correctly). If you’re clear about your choices, you can build your resume as per your chosen sector, and multiple versions for various sectors. For non-core profiles, focus mainly on one-page resumes. There are hardly any companies that ask for a 2-page resume, but best to be sure about the trend for your chosen sector.
The method for making a resume as I followed and would recommend is to first have a master excel sheet where you can collate all your achievements/ internships/ PoRs etc. Make it extensive, do not miss out on anything that you could possibly talk about (even achievements at school level), whether or not they are going to make it to the final resume. Follow this by marking those broad points (e.g. 3rd-year PoR, major internship, etc) that you think should go in the final resume. Once you have a rough idea of how much content you’ll be putting in, go through several resumes and pick a format that suits you best. Do not exaggerate and do not lie on your resume. You should be able to defend all points. For consulting resumes, as a standard format – every point should have your achieved result, what you did, and how you did it.
Go through enough consult resumes and you will learn to mold your points in this format.
Lastly, the most important ingredient of a good resume is the way it gets refined after each review. Get your resume reviewed by multiple friends and seniors. I had my resume reviewed by more than 10 seniors, and the final version is nowhere close to the first draft. Have your resume ready well in advance so you have enough time for reviews. It is advisable to edit your resume after each review and only then forward it to the next person to avoid redundancy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;placement-experience&quot;&gt;Placement experience:&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;pre-placement-preparation&quot;&gt;Pre-Placement Preparation:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;u&gt;Case Solving:&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;August/September&lt;/b&gt;: In the initial few months, I was still unsure about my backup options. I started doing basic prep – watching videos (Victor Cheng, CIC), reading up case prep best practices, understanding what consulting firms are exactly looking for, and how to best portray it. Apart from this, I practiced aptitude test questions since these tests were held by a lot of other companies. Through PT Cell, I gave some tests for incentive points on Pariksha. The papers wouldn’t be extremely difficult – but I would just use those to check which topics I was weak at. For some topics, I would then practice from a friend’s CAT material.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;October&lt;/b&gt;: Once the shortlists were out, I started to focus on just consulting (again, not advisable irrespective of the number of shortlists you have. Placements have a whole lot of luck at play), thus limiting most of my prep to case solving and HR. For case groups – I would suggest having 2, where you can have different frequencies for meeting up. At the start, it is better to have a group where you know each other well – since it accelerates the learning process through honest feedback. Along with the analytical/business skills, pay attention also to your body language and communication, and give and receive feedback for these too. After the shortlists, the buddies allotted by firms will solve cases with you. Their feedback and cases bring a significant boost to the prep. Also, start reaching out to other batchmates and schedule one-on-one case-solving sessions as you gradually grow more confident.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;November&lt;/b&gt;: This is usually when you tone down on the case group prep since its end sem time. Buddies are also not allowed to approach you for 2 weeks or so. I continued the HR prep, and got back to doing guesstimates – since I felt out of touch. Also, guesstimates are frequently asked in interviews, and not practising these once case-solving begins, is a common mistake. Additionally, brainstorm your resume with close case group friends, think of what kind of cases could be asked based on your internships/PoRs. Read newspapers regularly. (this is something you should start doing right away!) Towards the end, it is best to focus on revising important concepts that you may have come across, and only do enough cases so as to not lose touch. Stressing over not getting a case right during the last week is definitely not worth it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;u&gt;HR:&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HR prep seems to me like the most underrated part of placement prep. Most seniors I spoke to would say that it is something you leave for the last week, but I believe clumping it together in 1 week may not be the most effective way to do it. I would recommend having an excel sheet where you can note down some good questions from several interview prep books, consulting firm websites, etc. and go back to it every once in awhile, thinking of multiple examples from your experiences. A lot of the questions require you to think through and put forward your ideas in the best possible manner, and a lot of us need to practise telling our stories better – even if it is a seemingly simple “Tell me about yourself”. When your answers are ready, practise them out loud in front of the mirror, and even in front of your friends. Try talking about your experiences like you would to a colleague. Some people are comfortable with framing every word of their answer, while some like building on the basic concept. Choose what enables you to give your best. Be confident.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Answering strength/weakness questions: I figured early on – lying in interviews, in front of someone who has a lot of experience and is likely to see through it, was not a good idea. So while a lot of people recommend wrapping your weakness as if it were a strength, I decided to take an approach where I would be completely honest if asked. I noted down what I considered my weaknesses, took opinions from a couple of close friends, and then for each weakness, noted down how it had affected me and how I had worked on it so far. For strengths, it is best to talk about those which are the most relevant to the profile. Always back with examples or at least have them ready.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Communicating with interviewers during a disagreement: Remember that the same rules that work for people in real life will work in interviews. It is important to listen, be modest, and give only logical counter-arguments to the point being discussed. Back your arguments with valid examples or data, and if you realize you were incorrect earlier, be calm as you decide how to handle the situation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interview-experience&quot;&gt;Interview Experience:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I felt lucky to get a GD shortlist from P&amp;amp;G on day 0. (My lack of backups had started to bother me by then). I had to be present in LCH at around 3 pm on November 30th. After the first round, they selected some students to go to the second round of panel discussions. To be very honest, at that moment, I only wanted to revise cases and hoped this would end soon. But I got selected for the second round and was stuck in LCH for a very long time. However, it all ended on a good note, because – 1. They asked a variety of questions so I had had a thorough revision by the time the interviews were done, and 2. At around midnight, they declared the interview shortlist, which had my name.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On D-Day, I had interview slots with Bain, BCG, ATK, and P&amp;amp;G (in that order). All interviewers were extremely friendly, and so were the company officials (mostly our seniors) handling the process. I was handed an offer from BCG after 1 Principal round and 2 Partner rounds. Overall, I was asked one case based on my resume, one guesstimate picked from my “tell me about yourself” answer, and 2 other simple cases. I should mention here that these were much simpler than what we had practiced, and involved application of basic ideas and proper structuring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some questions I was asked (P&amp;amp;G + Consulting interviews)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
“Tell me about yourself”
“Can you tell me more about this internship”/“Tell me about the work you liked doing most as an E-Cell Events Manager”
“Tell me about a time you were able to create an impact through your work”
“What is that one project you are very proud of (can be during academic/intern/PoR)”
“Tell me about the time you successfully led a team”
“Tell me about a time you were able to eliminate/change an inefficient process”&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For these kinds of questions, quantify as much as you can. Talk about the challenges you faced, how you made your choices, how many stakeholders were involved, etc. – be specific.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;personal-takeaways&quot;&gt;Personal Takeaways:&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The entire placement process seems to put us outside our usual zones. Try your best to be patient and calm at all times. Be yourself – don’t panic and get anxious, since more pressure will stop you from giving your best at interviews. Try to establish some sort of connection with the interviewer. Most interviewers know that all candidates may have the skills to do the job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having personally known people who’ve cracked interviews after talking about football, or the best captains of the Indian Cricket Team, or which country they’d like to stay in – I am assured of the importance of being yourself in an interview over the attempt of trying to just impress the other person. One thing that really helped me was trying to understand the interviewer’s mindset, basically, to see why the process exists in the way it does. The interviewer is trying to talk to you to gauge if they would like to work with you, to have you in their team. He/she might be someone you see every day when you join. Would you be able to work with them every day, if you feel scared to talk to them?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An interview is just a conversation with someone senior who is trying to get to know you better, and your only responsibility here is to be true to them and yourself, and help them evaluate the possibility of working with you in an effective manner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And lastly, some friendly gyaan from being through one placement season :’)
Be there for your friends, throughout the process. Before and after you do or do not get through the shortlists or even when you get placed. The day/slot in which you get placed is not an indicator of how good you are, and everyone who has been through the process knows it well. It is a difficult time for everyone irrespective of how it looks to you, and the only way to get through this – is together. Your peers getting placed before you, or you losing your dream job/company, or anything else – while it may feel bad, don’t let it come in the way of acing your interview.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the best!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>2020-09-23</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/articles/2020-07/placements</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/articles/2020-07/placements</guid>
        
        
        <category>tips</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>A letter to Our-Quarantined-Selves</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Hi there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is the fourth day of the quarantine, mostly. Or it may be the seventh or the thirteenth. I seem to have lost count. But today, I’m finally here, writing. The last time I wrote, (which was more than a year ago), I was babbling endlessly about the streets and the people and the gelatos and pizzas of Italy. Fast-forward to now. Now. Now, I think of the cute old uncle who lived downstairs, by the waiting area. This sweet old man, full of life, always made it a point to talk to us when we went to the reception, weary and exhausted. Whether it was to collect a parcel, pay rent or some of the smaller struggles in the life of an exchange student living in a rented apartment; he would always make time for us – helping us translate stuff to English, asking us how we liked the Italian life, or talking about wanting to come to India someday. Now. Now, I’m usually tired of the endless tossing and turning in bed and waking up to updates of higher numbers affected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Numbers. 77. He must have been 77. I think to myself – Would he have made it? Someone who made my day several times – must he be doing okay? Will he be okay? Will I ever know? I don’t even know his name. I won’t ever be able to find out. All I know now are the numbers. As a kid, numbers were an absolute delight, and I loved playing with them. 146, 687, 83, 4 – tell me a number, and I’ll tell you something special about it. 4? This number now only reminds me of the number of people on the empty Centrale station of Milan. And I have dreams where people casually touch random surfaces, don’t wash hands correctly and whatnot. Honestly, it feels rather surreal. If I ever read a book about people across the globe dying, where the only way to save ourselves was to stay at home. Where the only way out was to not go see our friends and relatives, to not go to work. Where we were expected to not enjoy all those finer pleasures of life – a walk on the beach, listening to the waves crash, running across lush green meadows, watching a good play, brunch at a cute little cafe, or paint a sunset while watching one. Well, I would undeniably reckon that the author is just crass. Like which sane person (okay, not person, maybe force?) would want humans to stay away from each other? What are we, when not together? What kind of life has the underprivileged walk hundreds of miles just to get home? To be unable to afford food? Why increase problems for those who are barely able to make ends meet? For them to get stalled in a city where everything is unaffordable, away from their kids back in their hometowns?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I left home this morning (to get essentials, otherwise don’t leave your homes!). It was for the first time in around two weeks. I had already spent a significant amount of time homebound, anxious and melancholic; deprived of something. Something, that on the other days, would make everything worthwhile. Something that went missing and led to a feel of surrealism, a feeling that this is not who we were meant to be. This morning, when I walked down the street, I saw my city asleep. No cars. No autos whizzing by. No mundane chatter at the Kirana store. No children excitedly tugging at their parents to buy them knickknacks. I felt disheartened, but all it took to change that was a buzz on my phone, a reply from Sara.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://dododiaryhome.files.wordpress.com/2020/04/72d80f7090287dde18e333689e0ff653.jpg?w=892&amp;amp;h=1114&quot; alt=&quot;Smithsonian Image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sara was my host for a month in Milan, Italy. She now lives in the Cremona province, one of the worst affected regions in Italy. Sara wrote about how it was sad not to be able to take care of the elderly who lived far away or not to let the children out to play. But then she expressed how grateful she was. Grateful for doctors and health workers who had come in from faraway places. Grateful for those constructing hospitals, for those volunteering to deliver medicines. It reminded me of the day we were out in our balconies applauding all those who toil for us. It was at 5 PM that day, 120 seconds into that hullabaloo when it felt like something jolted me back in place. It was humans rejoicing together, standing in their balconies and creating a ruckus with their plates, spoons and conch shells. In those few seconds, I realised what the /something/ was, the /something/ that I was missing. Connection. The /something/ I believed with all my heart, was behind everything that we are, everything that we do, the cornerstone of who we’ve evolved into. I realised why I felt it would be absolutely shitty for a person to think and write a book about keeping people away from each other and saving the world. The essence of humanity, and you may realise it someday in the middle of chortles, vessels and raucous applause, is probably just connection. It brings us together; it keeps us sane.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is connection that helps someone living in the worst conditions spread love, gratefulness and optimism to someone staying continents apart. To talk about being positive, to appreciate the better things that such situations may bring along. Sara spoke about the bees returning to her house, the water returning clear to Venice, dolphins being spotted on the coasts and squirrels appearing in the parks. Clearly, we don’t need walks on the beaches or deafening club parties to feel a connection. It’s challenging times like these when we understand what connection is about, what being human is about. Sometimes, it manifests in the form of the desire to keep seeing your loved ones even if you can’t see them right away. Sometimes, the love for everyone who takes care of you unconditionally. And sometimes, the immense gratefulness towards technology that enables us to spread hope. Hope, that we get through this safe. Hope, that this is a moment of internalisation and reflection for all of us. Hope, that we get through this, and when we do, we still remember to love and care for the rest of us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Be human, stay safe, and Happy Quarantine?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lots of love,&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>2020-09-23</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/articles/2020-04/quarantine</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/articles/2020-04/quarantine</guid>
        
        
        <category>musings</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Year Ending &amp; New Beginnings - Part 2</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Around this time last year, I was seated in a flight that took me from Amsterdam to Milan, which was home back then. I wrote about how the year changed me and how I was grateful for the experience and hopeful for the future. 2018 was the year of the Firsts for me - my first formal internship, my first paycheck, my first time travelling abroad and even the first snowfall I ever witnessed, and the first time I thought of writing a blog. It had been overwhelming, and I could feel my words flow as I opened my notes App during the flight that day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is precisely what did not happen this year. I did not feel motivated enough for the new year, let alone come up with resolutions. 2019 was a year of learning as well, however, looking back, I couldn’t think of any &lt;em&gt;grand&lt;/em&gt; things that may have happened. And so, as 2020 began, I couldn’t find anything around me that was good enough to motivate me to do something worthwhile or special. As the days passed, I started noticing blips of positive triggers - the joy of seeing my plant grow, leaves changing colour, older ones fading, and fresh new ones making way for themselves - and for some reason, the beauty of it made me want to start doing something more with my life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I sit comfortably in this flight today that takes me back home to Mumbai, and not Milan, I realise that my experiences from a year ago continue to teach me. That although 2019 wasn’t as happening on paper, I surely am a different person today from who I was a year ago. As I delve deeper in introspection, I think about how the previous year has changed me. I am someone who firmly believes, in the simplest terms, that you are the story you tell yourself. And being lost and under-motivated for a while has helped me appreciate the importance of self-talk, and keeping yourself updated with your thoughts. It could be about thinking of where you stood once before vs where you stand now, or reflecting on what you were capable of doing a year ago, and what you are capable of doing now. The reason I believe in this exercise is that it helps you think, in more subjective and qualitative terms - what is it that you would like yourself to be able to do next? While this is a broad question to ask, I believe all of us know the answer to this on different levels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Earlier today, as I whiled away the hours at the airport, I couldn’t help but think now and then, about the beautiful three days I had spent, catching up with old friends and making new ones. Quite a change from the years before, the time spent at IIT Bombay had me challenge myself to initiate conversations, and eventually, I found myself merrily chatting with distant relatives or even friendly bus drivers in Austria. But the last couple of days have been lovely in a way few of those experiences were in terms of building that instant connection. Making new friends who feel as good as old and enjoying a good three days with someone supposedly not your type, is a win worth smiling back at. I bid goodbye to one such friend this morning, feeling as if I’d known her for at least a couple of months if not years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point, I can’t stop myself from trying to figure out how it worked, because I would love for it to happen again. Establishing a meaningful connection certainly makes our interactions worthwhile, for it makes us human. This nagging thought impels me to attempt to uncover - what is it that helps us bond? Is it the amount of time you’ve spent together? Is it the circumstances in which you met? Is it what was going through your mind at that moment? Is it about your preconceived notions about the other person? or is it the way you imagine them to behave and think, owing to subconscious stereotypes? I wonder if, in the end, it’s as simple as this: The ability to connect is a function of how two strangers will approach the interaction, which for a casual conversation, depends on:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;your image of the other person (What you think of them), and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;your image, as you believe the other person may be seeing (your notion of their opinion of you)
This inference is pretty debatable (so much so that I think I should not publish this at all, but if you do read, would love to know your thoughts). These two are pretty intertwined, in the sense that they are governed by your self-image and your view of the world, which again, are significantly correlated.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’ve made it so far, and are trying to figure out where I’m getting at with this, my answer to you would be - nowhere in particular. As a hopeful person who built a connection and had a good time over the last couple of days, I am hooked to the possibility of this happening to many others. I write this in an attempt to uncover the secret to getting there because I believe it will be very beautiful. It could be a world in which we connect to each other, a world where we can give without fear. Being hopeful about other people makes life beautiful - but much more so if you’re hopeful about yourself. The desire to add value to people’s lives keeps a lot of us going, but what makes life enjoyable is this willingness and the belief in our capabilities. The few times that our attempts may go in vain because of those who exploit the system, we should know it’s not a good enough reason for us to stop giving, to stop collaborating, to stop being hopeful or to stop believing in ourselves. It is impossible, or at the least extremely difficult, to trust in the power of collaboration if you don’t believe in the capabilities you own. It is only when are you confident about your own instincts, abilities and your little quirks that you can make life a positive-sum game for everyone. Is that the purpose? Trusting and leaving that to you :’)&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>2020-09-23</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/articles/2020-01/yearend2</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/articles/2020-01/yearend2</guid>
        
        
        <category>musings</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Un Semestre in Italia - The land of art, culture, and dreams</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;“Go for an exchange! It’s the best time of your life you get to spend with yourself!” When asked for one advice to give to anyone in insti, these were the words by a graduating senior. I still have four years, I said to myself then, but the thought stuck in the back of my mind. Time passed, and I never gave it a thought until a random late night discussion ended up in us looking for places we wanted to visit. Captivated by the canals and colors of Venice, I knew I was going on an Exchange, and I knew I was going to Europe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-planning--more-anxiety-than-excitement&quot;&gt;The planning – More anxiety than excitement:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being a ‘ghati’ since forever – someone who’d never stayed more than 10kms and two weeks away from home – I knew that convincing my parents for a semester away and that in another continent, was going to be difficult. Hardly did I know this was minuscule, compared to MEMS department’s procedure for sending students for exchange. We need separate approvals from every prof for every course matched, followed by FacAd approval and DUGC meetings – and at one point, I lost all hope and ended up grumbling about this unsupportive behavior to the HoD. At the end of this entire time- consuming process, I was only left with Politecnico di Milano, Italy – the European university whose deadline is last, the country where no one from insti had gone for exchange. First I was constantly anxious about getting nominated, then whether PoliMi would accept, and then if I’d ever get my visa on time. The day I finally got a Schengen stamped passport – I could no longer believe that my dream – the dream to be amidst canals in Venice – would come true. Very soon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://dododiaryhome.files.wordpress.com/2019/04/c2290220-4167-4d25-bbf7-d3640082e066.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Smithsonian Image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;and-it-begins&quot;&gt;And it begins!&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;first-things-first-&quot;&gt;First things first –&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Language issues. There aren’t as many English-speaking Italians as Indians. I did a lot of Italian on Duolingo, but with their accent, it becomes difficult to follow. However, they are incredibly kind and often go out of their way to help. For instance, the night we reached our home (for the first month), Mario – our AirBnB host who spoke only Italian and Spanish – couldn’t comprehend our questions regarding drinking water, and took us to a shop nearby so we could talk to the Bangladeshi shopkeeper and clear all our queries. What a gesture!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-university--academics-&quot;&gt;The University &amp;amp; Academics –&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The University was beautiful. One tour of the campus and you wouldn’t doubt that it ranks among the Top 10 universities for architecture and design. Built in 1863, it takes pride in being one of the best in Europe. It had an open campus – no solid boundary walls and over 40 buildings stretching over kilometers, and 7 campuses in all, 2 of which are in Milan. Classes were usually 2, 3 or 4 hours long, and there were some professors whose English sounded more like Italian. Course mapping was a struggle with the slot clashes and classes on different campuses. In class, the Italians with their red, blue, green pens and neon highlighters and printout of the slides as well as laptops on – stayed in alert mode throughout – continually paying attention and jotting down everything the prof says. Most courses had just an end-semester examination – of 30 marks – and grading was absolute. I couldn’t ultimately come up with a timetable without clashes, but the profs don’t expect you to attend all classes anyway. Passing is at 18 marks – and no, it is not easy to pass. You are expected to know EVERYTHING in detail – and most of the times the paper has just four broad questions – so if you’re not entirely prepared to write word-to-word answers – you’re going to have a tough time. The only good part is they let you take multiple attempts – but well, it only gets tougher with every attempt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://dododiaryhome.files.wordpress.com/2019/04/img_9717.jpg?w=1084&amp;amp;h=814&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;making-friends-&quot;&gt;Making friends –&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would thoroughly recommend staying in a student residence if there’s one. (This is also because we did face a lot of difficulties finding a new place after one month of AirBnB. Would not recommend that!). You get to interact directly and hang out with so many different people, helping you make the most of the exchange experience. However, most Italian universities usually do not provide that option, For me, it started with the orientation week, arranged with free food and drinks and opportunities to interact with exchange students from across the globe. It was all very new to me, and I stood there, anxious, unsure but also very excited, and it wasn’t long before I realized it was pretty much the case with a lot of people around. Somewhere between asking each other’s’ names and countries, struggling to say them right, and learning the basic words in our languages, we started feeling comfortable and at home in the foreign land. Punjabi music played at the end of the orientation, and Bhangda united us Indians as we taught our newly made friends the moves.  Soon followed the ESN (Erasmus Student Network) trips and parties, and I now had a nice group of 7-8 people to visit cool places with. Whether it was playing dumb charades in the Parco Sempione or weekend meetups where we relished each others’ cuisines or the road trip to Aosta in the Italian Alps or bringing in the New Year at home together or discussing dissimilarities in our cultures – it was an experience I want to live over and over again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://dododiaryhome.files.wordpress.com/2019/04/e52e1e41-8281-4f30-bf3b-473bd595b899.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
The time we played dumb charades in the park all day:)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://dododiaryhome.files.wordpress.com/2019/04/img_5531-1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;
Savoring the authentic pasta cooked by our Italian friend!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;making-the-most-out-of-schengen-&quot;&gt;Making the most out of Schengen –&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If there was one thing I knew I was going to do while on an exchange – it was to travel to as many places as possible. The moment I landed in Milano, I knew I wanted to remember every bit of this, and it gave birth to the idea of @pretty_yellow_lights, an Instagram handle where I would share my experiences every day. I traveled to 12 countries and had many enriching experiences. The beauty of every place was like none other, and owing to my schedule with classes only four days a week – we could easily take a Flixbus every Thursday night and be back in Milan on Monday morning. Flight tickets via RyanAir used to be very cheap – you could fly from Milan to Paris in a 1000 bucks (INR, yes!). We stayed in hostels, made spontaneous plans, cooked food from home for some long trips, survived on Turkish Kebaps for some. [When in Italy though, there’s always pizza :’)] I experienced the beautiful colors of autumn, and I experienced my first ever snowfall. There were the most obvious touristy places like Mt. Titlis in Switzerland, and there were the unfrequented beautiful lakes and parks of Slovenia. (Triglav National Park and Lake Bled, for the reference). Meeting fellow travelers and interactions with localities opened up new perspectives, leading to new ways of looking at life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://dododiaryhome.files.wordpress.com/2019/04/img_20181030_123040.jpg?w=313&amp;amp;h=345&amp;amp;zoom=2&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Slovenia, Switzerland, and Hungary&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;running-out-of-words&quot;&gt;Running out of words:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s so much to talk about, about being in Italy. I am so so so in love with the people there, and honestly, it’s difficult not to, for they pour their hearts into everything they do. You see them talking – the hand gestures and melody of their voices going in sync with their expressions – it makes you want to be a part of their world! And the food of course – making the most perfect pizzas and gelatos and having conversations with family and friends over long multiple-course meals, or even just the way they ensure perfection in the tiniest nooks and corners of their home – and how they build for themselves the prettiest surroundings ever. You leave home in the morning for class all sleepy – and then someone walking along the street with the most genuine smile ever will greet you with a ‘Buon giorno!’ You reach the metro but don’t know what train to take, and someone walks you to the exact place at the other end of the station, just because they want to help you out. Yes, there are language issues – hardly would you come across anyone on the streets who would speak English that is half as good. Yes, some days you are going to be tired to get out of bed and cook for yourself. Yes, there are going to be some days when you miss family and miss insti. But with people so kind (and food so delicious), you don’t want to miss this one chance. I miss the happy ‘Ciao!’s exchanged with merry strangers – shopkeepers, passengers on metros and bus drivers. I remember how cars patiently wait for pedestrians to cross, smiling while asking me to go first. I learned to appreciate art, culture and the Italian way of life – living every moment and giving the best at what you pursue. Exchange gave me the time to be with myself, to think and to grow as a person. Oh, and well, it inspired me to start writing (No semex = no dodo-diaries). The only apt line to conclude with would be “Go for an exchange! It’s the best time of your life you get to spend with yourself!”  :’)&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>2020-09-23</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/articles/2019-04/semex</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/articles/2019-04/semex</guid>
        
        
        <category>tips</category>
        
        <category>travel</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>From 'Fruhstuck' to 'Tetris'- thoughts of an eternally hopeful introvert</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I stand inside the elevator in Nuremberg trying to figure out which floor we have to get to. ‘Frühstück’, it says next to level ‘-1’. I try multiple times to get it right, but something in the way I read it doesn’t make it sound original enough. As if I am attempting for no reason to do something because those around me are doing it well, as if I’m trying too hard to fit in. Which makes me think, maybe people waste so much energy being the people they don’t need to be? Maybe in life we set our goals not as per our skills or traits, but try too hard to be ‘successful’, in the parameters society sets for us. What we do fail to realise, however, is that all of us are so damn different, that our paths and for that matter our end-goal of success, just cannot be the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://dododiaryhome.files.wordpress.com/2019/02/apps.43965.14560640085442649.ccdfc4bc-a07e-4450-ae10-dc0a9d70ca14.jpg?w=247&amp;amp;h=247&amp;amp;zoom=2&quot; alt=&quot;Smithsonian Image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One reason why travelling and meeting new people and knowing more about them is so important is to get a firsthand experience of how different every person out there is. We know how different we are when we can’t even speak words the way they’re used to hearing it, or how we don’t have the words for some feelings like they do. Which gets us to how in spite of being from similar cultural backgrounds too, everyone has their own story, their own strengths and traits that would render comparing one person to another unjust. And doesn’t that compel you to think, there must be a reason why we’re all so different? And just because maybe your peers and family and everyone else appreciated that one person who apparently, is successful, say got that coveted job, would you do the same? That by doing the same things as everyone else, aren’t we just messing up with the way the universe was designed (and if there’s such a thing?). My randomly racing train of thoughts comes to a halt as we reach level ‘-1’, and I realise I thought too much in the few seconds in the elevator. I think if that puts me in the category of ‘crazy’ – never-ending randomly-running thought trains triggered by a word I read somewhere. But isn’t that almost every introvert ever? I wonder, I wish. Isn’t it plain sad how it sometimes feels that humans by design are kind of biased towards extroverts? I learnt through multiple incidents spread across my childhood, and sometimes the hard way too, to eventually enjoy ‘stuff’ that extroverts are inherently good at – stuff like greeting people on the streets and going out with a lot of people and also enjoying it, to the point that most people would affirm I am far from their image of an introvert. I’ve learnt, however, that it’s only when you get there do you realise why it is important to constantly challenge yourself, for I am now someone who is wholeheartedly grateful to the close-knit set of people I can share my ideas with. There are some unusual enlightening perspectives that stem from the amalgamation of the abilities of introverts and extroverts; the advancements we could make by just communicating, by the exchange of knowledge, the sharing of ideas. One of these days my friend said he would do this particular amazing thing in life because, he said, ‘I have the ability so I’m going to do it’. Words that sound so simple, but are vital for every person to etch into their minds. So many of us stop ourselves from achieving greatness as we settle for what feels like the good bet. Each of us has the capability to do so much, to contribute in a unique manner, to fight for something that only we can achieve. Maybe some of us are good at generating the ideas, maybe some of us at putting them out to the world. Maybe all of us with our different unique ideas add up like a perfect game of Tetris. Lets not allow anyone else define what success ought to be, let us go out and collaborate and fearlessly share our ideas. It’s time we put in our best, doing the things that we want to do, following our passions, pushing our limits, fighting against what confines us. To break free from the shackles of what holds us back, be it lethargy or fear of judgement. Let us acknowledge the power of collaboration and bank on our idiosyncrasies to add value to people’s lives, because no one else has the ability to change the world in the way you can.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>2020-09-23</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/articles/2019-02/fruhstuck</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/articles/2019-02/fruhstuck</guid>
        
        
        <category>musings</category>
        
        <category>travel</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Some Year End/Beginning Thoughts</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;My roommate once asked me what I did on NYE. It’s this. I look back and write what comes to my mind. All the people I learnt from, all the experiences that changed me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2018 has been exceptionally good to me. It’s changed too many things about me, except for this one. This one habit of looking at the positive side of things. Because I’ve been having these ‘Oh this year was so nice’ feelings since as long as I can remember. It was only this time that I understood. It was because I looked at the good experiences, and the good consequences of seemingly bad ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the same time, I am not a particularly optimistic person. I have a tendency to be unsure of how everything will turn out. Like I was, one year ago. But 2018 has been far from disappointing. For one, it has left me more mature than I started off with. The ability to pull off small talk with extended family for someone who rushed to the bathroom to avoid conversations, is a visibly large step in the right direction. The ability to cook a wholesome nutritious indian meal for someone who hardly contributed to the kitchen, is another. Knowing you are completely responsible for yourself and home is now 4000 miles and several months away, for the first time ever, is a complete U-turn to the way you run your life.
This year, I met several people. People I built deep bonds with, people I respect, people to care for, people I wouldn’t want to live without, and people I’ll probably never meet again. Of course, these sets are not mutually exclusive. But I learnt to accept that some people are meant to stay only so long, some people have only so much to teach us. That our time with everyone we claim to be connected with, is limited. That it is important to be ourselves and equally important to keep learning and keep growing from our experiences. So when you meet the people you know you probably wouldn’t meet again, don’t be afraid. Don’t be afraid to create a valued bond fearing it may not stay. Do justice to everything life throws your way, and live it to the fullest. Win or learn (which is also winning, btw)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I met some of the most amazing people and built some beautiful relationships this year. Like God decided to handpick some of the best people and have them walk into my life randomly. People who don’t get much of your time but go out of their way to do things for you. People who cared a lot, and yes, people who messed up. It sometimes feels as if everything has started to make sense. As if the pieces fit. The dots now connect.
The good experiences made me happy. The bad ones made me wiser. I’m grateful. It feels like all the pieces were coming together as I was busy seizing a day at a time. And that I now have a greater responsibility, given I’ve had my fair share of opportunities landing themselves my way. Now, I have to go seek those out. That with the battles now fought, it’s time to gather all that I’ve collected. That with the renewed strength, the optimism and sagacity, its time to make the world a better place. :’)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>2020-09-23</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/articles/2018-12/year-end-v2</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/articles/2018-12/year-end-v2</guid>
        
        
        <category>musings</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>A Happy First :)</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;You want one with the mountains in the background?” I shiver my way through a nod, glad about finding people who’re partly happy and partly wondering how this girl, probably Indian, got to this place where the wind and snow hit her face. It’s something I was completely happy and anything but prepared, for. I think they could see that glitter in my eyes, like it was probably the day I had waited for, for a long long time. And I sat there, at a corner of the cable car, holding on to my little bag as if it would keep me warm, because neither did I have gloves nor the right shoes. Every time I entered a new cable car, I’d greet the people, ask them where they were from. There were Germans, there were Austrians, there were people aged 20, and people 45 and kids who were probably just 5! What a lucky set of people, I thought, getting to enjoy snowfall at this age, while I had to wait for 22 years. But it was worth it. All that I saw, all that I felt. Whether it was the gush I felt as I saw rain outside the cable car turn to snow as it ascended, or the first time I came out and felt the first flake on my fingers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s always such a trade off, you know? Whether you want to live that moment you’ve always waited for, or capture it so you can live it again. After having my fill of the snow getting into my hair and the moment where my hands and legs got cold and I saw that it was -4 degrees, I decided to take my phone out (while I could barely even hold it) and then went on to record a clip of myself, trying to cherish the moment, but all I could say was &lt;em&gt;I’m so happy omgodd I’m so happy I can’t even explain how happy I am right now and it’s cold here, will I die, but I always wanted to experience snowfall before I die so maybe it’s okay if I die now&lt;/em&gt;. I do not know what that feeling is called, I’ve never experienced it before, but in that moment, I felt like the luckiest and was definitely the happiest person on the planet. As a series of cable cars took me to the top, I met a lot of people, everyone in their skiing outfits. A guy from Germany who let me go first, and another who happily clicked a picture, and another 10 year old girl who curiously looked at me all the while, assuring me with her silent glances that I was going to be okay, and that it was okay to feel cold as even she was. She didn’t speak English, and I don’t know how she did it, but definitely brought peace to my partly scared mind. I asked her where she was from, but she didn’t speak English, so she nudged her mom, who told me they were from Germany. On the last cable car to the top of Salzburg, I met a lady from Vienna. She told me where I should go once we reached, and also asked me where I was from. And then with the most genuine smile ever, she said, ‘Is that why you’re so happy?’
‘Yes’, I replied, ‘&lt;b&gt;It’s my first snowfall’&lt;/b&gt;. :’)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>2020-09-23</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/articles/2018-10/my-first-blog</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/articles/2018-10/my-first-blog</guid>
        
        
        <category>travel</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
